"Ginkgo Biloba as a Brain Health Supplement for Dementia"
More than a third
of older Americans
take some kind
of brain health supplement
to the tune
of billions of dollars a year,
and one of the most popular
is ginkgo biloba.
U.S. household surveys suggest
as many as 2 percent
of Americans
are taking gingko supplements.
Ginkgo biloba's a tree
with fan-shaped leaves,
regarded as a living fossil,
having persisted
relatively unchanged
for over
a quarter billion years.
Its resilience makes it
a favorite of urban planners,
hardy enough to survive
even a nuclear blast,
as one of the few survivors
within a short radius
of ground zero in Hiroshima.
Over the last 30 years or so,
an extract of gingko leaves
has become one of the most
widely used herbal treatments
for dementia.
A 2009 Cochrane review
of three dozen
randomized controlled trials
involving more than
4,000 participants
concluded that
the "evidence that ginkgo biloba
has predictable and clinically
significant benefit
for people with dementia
or cognitive impairment
is inconsistent
and unreliable."
One trial showed
very large benefits,
but others showed
no effect at all.
To put the subject to rest
once and for all,
two large randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
were conducted, one in Europe,
funded by a gingko
supplement manufacturer,
and the largest,
longest study to date,
funded by the NIH
in the United States.
More than 5,000
older men and women
with either normal cognition
or mild cognitive impairment
were randomized to
a gingko leaf extract or placebo
for five or six years
to see if it would prevent them
from sliding into dementia.
Mild cognitive impairment
is the intermediate
clinical state
between normal cognition
for one's age and dementia.
The conversion rate
of MCI to dementia
is about 10 percent per year.
The bottom line?
Neither trial
showed any clear benefit,
definitively demonstrating
no preventative effect.
However, for those
already suffering with dementia,
gingko leaf extracts do appear
to slow cognitive decline
compared to placebo
for those with Alzheimer's,
or dementia
more broadly defined.
Of course that's assuming
there's actually gingko
in your gingko supplements.
Investigations
of gingko supplements
off the shelves
in both Europe and the U.S.
found some that had
no apparent gingko at all.
As high as about
one in six ginkgo supplements
appeared to be all filler,
without any detectable
ginkgo biloba DNA.
Side-effects-wise,
at typical doses,
such as 120 mg twice a day,
ginkgo extracts may cause
mild stomach upset,
headache, dizziness,
constipation,
and allergic skin reactions.
Higher dosages can result
in restlessness, diarrhea,
nausea, vomiting, and weakness.
There have been about a dozen
published case reports
of bleeding
associated with gingko,
but thankfully
this did not surface
in systematic reviews
of the dementia studies.
Still, out of
an abundance of caution,
it's been recommended to
stop taking gingko supplements
at least two weeks
before elective surgery.
The bottom line,
according to a recent review
of Alzheimer's disease
therapies,
is that ginkgo
is one of the few things
that can beat out placebo
for cognitive function.